<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Sue's Blog</title><link>https://yl238.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on Sue's Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- 0.147.1</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 May 2025 10:50:10 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yl238.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Using LLMs to Evaluate Youtube Videos</title><link>https://yl238.github.io/posts/summarise-youtube-video/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 May 2025 10:50:10 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://yl238.github.io/posts/summarise-youtube-video/</guid><description>&lt;p>I often get recommended YouTube videos with catchy titles but not much substance. To avoid wasting time, I built a simple app that grabs the transcript of the video, feeds it to ChatGPT, and generates a quick summary, key moments, and any fresh insights the video offers. After skimming this I can decide whether it’s worth watching the video. It’s been a huge time-saver, so I’m sharing the code here, along with a quick overview of how it works.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Create a Static Blog with Hugo, PaperMod and Github Pages</title><link>https://yl238.github.io/posts/hugo-papermod-gh/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 May 2025 20:50:10 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://yl238.github.io/posts/hugo-papermod-gh/</guid><description>&lt;p>This article describes how I built this blog using the &lt;a href="https://gohugo.io/">Hugo&lt;/a> framework and the &lt;a href="https://git.io/hugopapermod">PaperMod&lt;/a> theme; and how to host it on &lt;a href="https://pages.github.com/">GitHub Pages&lt;/a>. Unlike most tutorials, my approach stores the source code in a private GitHub repository while serving the site from a public GitHub Pages repository.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="hugo">Hugo&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://gohugo.io/">Hugo&lt;/a> is a popular open-source static website generator. Written in Go, it is very fast to build and serve. Like Jekyll, you can write the blog posts using Markdown and Hugo will natively render the markdown files to HTML pages. It supports many themes, including PaperMod, which is very flexible and pleasing to look at.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Time Series Forecasting Methods (Part 1): Exponential Smoothing and ARIMA</title><link>https://yl238.github.io/posts/exp-smoothing-arima/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 May 2025 14:29:53 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://yl238.github.io/posts/exp-smoothing-arima/</guid><description>&lt;p>Time series forecasting refers to the use of historical data to predict future values, and enabling the identification of patterns and trends that inform decision-making. An example time series is the UK Retail Sales Index for electrical household appliances from 1988 to 2025 (Figure 1), which provides seasonally adjusted retail sales in Great Britain in both value and volume terms. The ability to accurately forecast such data is crucial, as it helps business stakeholders and policymakers make well-informed decisions in scenarios such as setting economic policies, managing inventory or planning staffing requirements.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Edinburgh Data Science Meetup</title><link>https://yl238.github.io/posts/edinburgh-data-science/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 15:49:48 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://yl238.github.io/posts/edinburgh-data-science/</guid><description>&lt;p>Recently I gave a presentation at the &lt;a href="https://www.meetup.com/edinburgh-data-science-ai/">Edinburgh Data Science Meetup&lt;/a> on time-series forecasting. In particular, comparing the differences between traditional methods such as ARIMA and Exponential Smoothing with the latest Deep Learning models. Hopefully I will turn these into blog posts in the coming months, but in the meantime you can download the presentation here.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img alt="First Page Preview" loading="lazy" src="https://yl238.github.io/posts/edinburgh-data-science/cover-page.png">&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="margin-top: 20px;">
&lt;a href="https://yl238.github.io/posts/edinburgh-data-science/edinburgh-ds-meetup-sueliu.pdf" download style="display: inline-block; padding: 10px 20px; background-color: #007acc; color: white; border-radius: 5px; text-decoration: none;">
⬇️ Download Full PDF
&lt;/a>
&lt;/div></description></item></channel></rss>