<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Obsidian on Sue's Blog</title><link>https://yl238.github.io/tags/obsidian/</link><description>Recent content in Obsidian on Sue's Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- 0.147.1</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 May 2025 17:16:10 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yl238.github.io/tags/obsidian/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How I use Obsidian</title><link>https://yl238.github.io/posts/using-obsidian/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 May 2025 17:16:10 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://yl238.github.io/posts/using-obsidian/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://obsidian.md/">Obsidian&lt;/a> is an extremely versatile note-taking and knowledge-management app that uses plain text Markdown files stored locally. It&amp;rsquo;s great at creating connections between notes through backlinks, and many people use it to build personal knowledge bases. Furthermore, its flexibility allows it to be used in many different ways. This post describes how I use Obsidian in my professional life and will hopefully be of interest to others.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="obsidian-for-managers">Obsidian for Managers&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I manage three machine learning engineering teams at a tech company, each working on completely different projects. I need to run stand-ups, attend various meetings with stakeholders, interview candidates, and try to do some hands-on development. I am not an expert in the areas I manage, but I need to have a high-level understanding and be able to provide direction. This means I must constantly learn about many areas, both technical and otherwise, and review what I&amp;rsquo;ve learned. What I need is a way to easily capture information, review it later, and take action. Obsidian is perfect for this purpose.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>